Sodachi Lost
Oikura's goal.
What does she—
want to know?
Very well. Let's look at the questions we have
concerning her mother's disappearance again.
じゃ もう一度最初から
お母さんの失踪についての疑問点を まとめてみよっか
End Story
やっぱり私としては そこが肝だと思うんだよね
It's my feeling that it's the key to solving this mystery.
つまり どうして部屋の鍵はかかっていたのか
Primarily, we don't know
わからないな
why her mother's room was locked.
ああ わからない
Yeah, we don't.
You don't know?
わからないんですかあ?
なーんかがっかりだなあ
その程度の密室の謎がわからないなんて
I'm disappointed that you're incapable of solving a simple locked room mystery.
I knew that you were a fool, Araragi,
阿良々木先輩が愚かなのは知っていましたけれど
but I'm surprised you prove to be a fool as well, Hanekawa.
羽川先輩 あなたまでが愚かだなんて
いや どうしても気になって 出過ぎた真似とは思いつつ
様子を見に来たんですよ
Oh, I felt I shouldn't come here,
but my curiosity overruled my feelings.
ひょっとすると羽川先輩じゃあ
阿良々木先輩の力にはなれないんじゃないかって
I suppose I was worried that you wouldn't be able to help him after all, Hanekawa.
すると案の定でした
As I feared, then.
あはは やっぱり全盛期じゃなくなってるんじゃないですか?
It's just not like it was in your heyday, huh?
あはは あはは
It amuses me somewhat that you were still able to snatch Araragi
それなのに その程度で私から
阿良々木先輩をかっさらって行ったとか
away from me.
笑えるなあ いやはや
How amusing that you could tempt him with your udders.
そんな胸部の肉塊で阿良々木先輩を誘惑した割に ねえ?
はっはっは
She's holding such a huge grudge.
すげえ根に持ってる
ああ 恥ずかしいなあ 恥ずかしいなあ
Gosh, how embarrassing.
私だったら恥ずかしくて生きていけないなあ
I would want to die from shame if I were you.
阿良々木先輩に色仕掛けで自分を選ばせておいて
それでむしろご迷惑をおかけするなんて
First you used your body to make him choose you, and all it led to is more trouble for Araragi.
いや思えば私も自分が情けないですよ
Though, thinking about it, I should be ashamed as well.
私がご一緒していれば
阿良々木先輩にそんな思いをさせることはなかったのに
He would not have had to struggle had I been with him,
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
みすみす羽川先輩のおっぱいに
奪われてしまったばかりに こんなことになって
but this happened because I allowed you to steal him with your breasts.
阿良々木先輩に心細い思いをさせてしまって
申し訳ありません
I'm very sorry I put you through this disheartening situation.
本当 思いますよ
Honestly, I am.
あのとき阿良々木先輩が私を選んでくれていたらって
What if he had picked me, I think to myself.
でも責めません!
But I don't blame you.
私は阿良々木先輩を責めませんよ
I really don't, Araragi.
責めませんとも
I don't blame you.
誰にだってミスはありますからねえ
Everyone makes mistakes.
ねえ 羽川先輩?
Right, Hanekawa?
You'll forgive him too, right?
羽川先輩も許して差しあげますよね?
阿良々木先輩があなたを選ぶという
大きなミスを犯したことを
Forgive him that he made the
grave mistake of choosing you.
なんだったら 口に出して言って差し上げたらどうですか?
You should tell him you're sorry now.
"私の愚かさはあなたの責任じゃないよ 阿良々木くん"って
"It's not your fault that I'm a fool, Araragi."
Hey, Ougi—
おい 扇ちゃん—
I already know...
私には
私にはもう解けちゃってますけどね
I already know what happened
in that locked room.
その密室
それにお母さんはどこに行ったのかも
And also what happened to her mother.
まあ 概ね
More or less.
それなりに
In a sense.
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part Three
まあ私にとっては非常に簡単な練習問題でしたけれど
To me it was an exceedingly simple exercise.
羽川先輩 どうしてもわからないというのであれば
私は皆さんのいい後輩でありたいですからね
If you can't figure it out for yourself, Hanekawa, I can try to support my elders.
巨乳を謝っていただければ
私は鷹揚(おうよう)な対応を考えていますよ
If you apologize for being well-endowed, I intend to react benevolently.
"おっぱいに全部栄養を回してしまいました
"Everything I ate went straight to my breasts."
年下で後輩の扇ちゃん この簡単な問題が私にはどうしても解けないので
答を教えてください
"I'm incapable of solving this simple problem,
so please help me, Ougi."
もう二度と阿良々木くんを横取りしませんから"
"I won't snatch Araragi away from you again."
とお願いするのであれば
模範解答を提示してあげなくもありません
If you ask for it, I might just give you the sample solution.
Ougi!
扇ちゃん!
I'll ask for it!
僕がお願いするよ
You're okay with that, right?
それでいいだろ
If you know the solution, tell us.
わかっているんなら 教えてくれ
三年前 老倉母子に何があったのかを
What happened three years ago to Oikura and her mother?
えー 困ったなあ
This puts me in a bind.
羽川先輩には 私は本当に怒っているんですけれど
阿良々木先輩に頼まれちゃあ断れないかなあ
I am honestly mad at Hanekawa,
but I don't think I can turn down Araragi.
Don't bore us with your silence.
黙っちゃって つまらないなあ
所詮 あなた
実際は全盛期でも大したことなかったんじゃないですか?
I'm starting to think you weren't
very impressive in your heyday either.
いいですよ
All right.
じゃあ 阿良々木先輩
Listen then, Araragi.
"羽川とかいう大したことのない奴を
選んだのは間違いでした
"It was a mistake to choose someone as insignificant of a person as Hanekawa."
僕のパートナーは扇ちゃんしかいません
"I have no partner but you."
羽川よりも扇ちゃんのほうが好きです"
"I like you more than Hanekawa."
と言うのであれば 教えて上げますよ
Say that and I'll tell you.
Whatever we call the truth.
ことの真相とやらを
What is it?
どうしたんですか?
There's no reason to hesitate.
迷う必要なんてないでしょう
You see, once Oikura is told as well,
だって それがわかれば 老倉先輩は間違いなく
I am sure she'll be very happy.
お喜びになられるんですから
Isn't this the time to be repaying your debt to her?
今こそあなたは
老倉先輩に恩返しをすべきときなんじゃないですか?
それとも結局 なんだかんだ言いつつ
羽川先輩の胸が優先ですか?
Or will you choose Hanekawa's breasts by way of some flimsy excuse?
Hanekawa may be forced
to admit defeat by Ougi.
I don't want Hanekawa to admit defeat.
Stop, Araragi.
やめてね 阿良々木くん
そんなことを言わないで
Don't say it.
Even if you'd lie, or do it for my sake, I don't want you to say that.
たとえ嘘でも 私のためでも
私は阿良々木くんにそんなことを言って欲しくない
But Hanekawa...
だ だけど羽川
むろん 私も言わない
Of course, I won't say what she wants either.
私は何度だって
阿良々木くんを横取りする
I'll steal him away from you anytime.
Ougi, give me ten seconds, and I will prove to you
扇ちゃん 十秒頂戴
証明するわ
that Araragi was right in choosing me.
私を選んだ阿良々木くんが正しかったと
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
Ten.
じゅう
Nine.
きゅう
Eight.
はち
Seven.
Six.
ろく
Five.
Four.
よん
Three.
さん
Hanekawa is thinking.
Two.
One.
いち
Hanekawa is thinking.
Ze—
Enough.
ぜろは数えなくていい
I win.
私の勝ち
Sodachi Lost
I win.
だけど これは...
But...
Did you...
あなた...
あなた 最初にこんなことを思いついたの?
Was this really your first idea?
Without a more detailed investigation?
精査するまでもなく?
Just by overhearing fragments of our conversation?
私達の話を 断片的に聞いて
And still you reached this conclusion first?
それで まず思いついたのが
こんな真相?
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
Yes.
発想はそこからですね
I had an idea,
そう直感して
そこから推理の辻褄(つじつま)合わせです
let my intuition guide me and
adjusted the reasoning to the facts.
どういうものの考えかたしてるの あなた...
Your way of thinking is screwed up.
正気の沙汰(さた)じゃないよ
こんなのを最初に思いつくなんて
No sane human being would think of this solution first.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
あなただって最終的にはその真相に至ったんでしょう?
You eventually came to the same conclusion.
だったらそんなことを言われる覚えはありませんよ
Who are you to be throwing stones?
The one whose sanity comes into question is someone else entirely.
それに もっとも正気の沙汰じゃないのは
Oikura, right?
老倉先輩でしょう?
She's the one without a shred of sanity in her.
あのかたが一番
ぶっちぎりで正気の沙汰じゃない
—What does that even mean?
Araragi, we can't.
阿良々木くん 駄目だ
これは 絶対に老倉さんには言えない
We can't tell this to Oikura.
さっき 阿良々木くんは
どんな真相でも伝えるつもりだったみたいだけれど
I think you would have told her whatever the truth was,
これを聞けば
さすがに気が変わると思う
but I think your attitude will change once you hear it.
It will?
気が変わるって
駄目ですよお 羽川先輩
No, no, Hanekawa.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
Don't spoil the fool.
愚か者を甘やかしちゃあ
We have to let him think for himself.
少しは自分で考えさせてあげないと
でないと阿良々木先輩は
いつまでも愚かなままです
Otherwise he will be a fool forevermore.
No matter how much time passes
We have to help him towards the truth.
阿良々木先輩にも思いつかせてあげないと
思いつくだけで気持ち悪くなるような
A truth that makes you sick
ことの真相を
the moment you hit upon it.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Red
The worst truth I can imagine...
僕が思いつく 最悪の真相と言えば
ヒント１
Hint one.
Oikura's mother is already dead.
老倉先輩のお母様はもう亡くなっています
Dead...
死んでる...
ってことは
So...
そう...
Yeah...
老倉のお母さんを殺したのが
老倉のお父さんとか
Then I guess Oikura's father killed her mother,
奇妙な失踪は 神隠しのような消失は
それゆえに起こった何かで
and the reason she disappeared
is because of whatever happened there.
全然違います
Completely wrong.
お優しいですねえ 阿良々木先輩は
How naive you are, Araragi.
想定しうる最悪の真相が
そんなぬるいものだとは
Is a lame theory like that the worst you could possibly think of?
では羽川先輩
All right, Hanekawa.
ヒント２をどうぞ
Hint two, please.
わ 私?
Y-You want me to?
Hint two.
ヒント２
Just like you mistook her home for a ruin,
阿良々木くんが中学生の頃老倉さんの家を
廃屋だと勘違いしていたのと同じように
Oikura was also mistaken about her mother.
老倉さんもまたひとつ お母さんについて
勘違いをしていた
She still is.
今もしている
So... Oikura's mother was killed by Oikura, but she doesn't remember it?
お母さんは殺されていて... 犯人が老倉で
本人はそれを自覚していない... とか?
ヒント３
Hint three.
密室からの消失は必ずしも
密室からの脱出ではない
Disappearing from a locked room
doesn't necessarily mean they left it.
つまり 老倉が鍵を開けて
中に這入ったとき
So when Oikura unlocked the door,
お母さんはまだ部屋の中にいて
こっそり老倉の後ろを通って家から出て行った?
her mother was hiding behind the door or something and snuck out after her?
何の意味があるんですか それ
Why would anybody do that?
Hint four.
ヒント４
If she's already dead, why hasn't the corpse been found?
阿良々木くん お母さんが亡くなっているなら
そのご遺体は どうして見つからないのかしら
Why is she still listed as missing?
どうして老倉さんのお母さんは
失踪扱いのままなの?
Missing Person Report
Hint five.
ヒント５
今回 私は又聞きでしたが
仮に阿良々木先輩が私をパートナーに選んでくれていたとしても
I based my solution on what I heard from you,
but even if you had picked me as your partner,
老倉先輩の話からでは "それ"については
正確なところがわからなかったでしょう
there would have been something I couldn't have determined.
What is it?
さて "それ"は何
Hint six.
ヒント６
老倉さんの前の家は 片付けまでは手が回らず
ゴミ屋敷状態だった
Oikura's last home was too large to clean for her, and it turned into a big mess.
ヒント７
Hint seven.
お母様はある日突然いなくなった
Her mother had disappeared suddenly one day.
ある日突然 あの日突然
One day, a certain day.
では その前日はどうだったのでしょう?
What about the day before?
Hint eight.
ヒント８
ご家庭の崩壊のことで 老倉さんのお母さんの心は
酷く弱っていた
Oikura's mother suffered greatly from her divorce.
So much she locked herself in her room.
部屋に閉じこもってしまうほどに
生きる気力を失うほどに
Enough to lose the will to live.
Hint nine.
ヒント９
お母様の面倒を見ていた老倉先輩ですが
お母さまはそのうち食事を全然召し上がらなくなったそうですね
Oikura cooked for her mother,
but her mother stopped eating completely.
I'm sure you independently toned down the word "completely" here
で ここで言う"全然"を 阿良々木先輩
"でも そうは言っても少しくらいは食べてたんだろ?"
Completely
という意味に 勝手にマイルドに解釈しませんでした?
to mean that she still ate a little.
Hint ten.
ヒント10
老倉さんはお母さんが いつからか話しかけてもまったく応えなくなったとも
言っていたわよね
Oikura said her mother stopped
responding when she spoke to her.
Hint eleven.
ヒント11
部屋の隅から 動かなくなったとも
She stopped leaving the corner of the room.
Hint twelve.
ヒント12
She
didn't
eat.
She didn't eat.
食べなくて
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
eat.
She
didn't
listen.
She didn't listen.
聞いてなくて
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
listen.
She
didn't
speak.
She didn't speak.
喋らなくて
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
speak.
She
didn't
move.
She didn't move.
動かない
Is that still life?
これって 生きていると思う?
ヒント13
Hint thirteen.
中学生が本当に 何年もに亘って
引きこもった親の面倒なんて見切れるものですかねえ
Can someone in middle school really take care of their reclusive parent for years?
A corpse would be manageable.
死体の面倒ならばともかくとして
Hint fourteen.
ヒント14
How long can a corpse be identified as such?
人間の死体はいつまで原形を保っていられるかな
ヒント15
Hint fifteen.
Hint sixteen.
ヒント16
Hint seventeen.
ヒント17
Hint eighteen.
ヒント18
Hint nineteen.
ヒント19
Hint twenty.
ヒント20
Hint twenty-one.
ヒント21
Hint twenty-two.
ヒント22
Hint twenty-three.
ヒント23
Hint twenty-four.
ヒント24
Hint twenty-five.
ヒント25
Hint twenty-six.
ヒント26
Hint twenty-seven.
ヒント27
Hint twenty-eight.
ヒント28
Hint twenty-nine.
ヒント29
Hint thirty.
ヒント30
Hint thirty-one.
ヒント31
Hint thirty-two.
ヒント32
Hint thirty-three.
ヒント33
Hint thirty-four.
ヒント34
Hint thirty-five.
ヒント35
Hint thirty-six.
ヒント36
Hint thirty-seven.
ヒント37
Hint thirty-eight.
ヒント38
Hint thirty-nine.
ヒント39
Hint forty.
ヒント40
Hint forty-one.
ヒント41
Hint forty-two.
ヒント42
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
Hint forty-three.
ヒント43
Hint forty-four.
ヒント44
Hint forty-five.
ヒント45
Hint forty-six.
ヒント46
Hint forty-seven.
ヒント47
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
Hint forty-eight.
ヒント48
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
Hint forty-nine.
ヒント49
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
Hint fifty.
ヒント50
I got it, goddamn!
わかったよ もう!
要は老倉は ほとんど二年間!
母親の死体の面倒を見てきたってことだろ!?
Oikura looked after a corpse for almost two years, right?
The corpse rotted away until everything was gone.
死体が腐り果てて 消えてなくなるまで
And she didn't realize it!
それと気付かずに!
Yes.
ああ そうだ
I overlooked the truth two years ago
during the class meeting.
二年前の学級会で 僕は真相を見逃した
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
Oikura's
insanity
tragedy
—
五年前の廃屋でも見逃した
I overlooked it five years ago.
I
六年前の幼なじみは 未だ思い出せない
Even now I can't remember what happened six years ago.
なればこそ
That is why
ここで逃げちゃあいけない
I cannot run away here.
must confront it.
ここで誤魔化しちゃあいけない
I have to look it in the eye.
ご名答
Correct answer.
Oikura's mother didn't suddenly disappear.
老倉先輩のお母様は突然いなくなったんじゃない
絶食によってゆっくりと餓死したんです
She slowly starved to death.
そしてそのあと ゆっくりと腐っていった
Then she slowly rotted away.
原形がわからないほどに腐乱して 溶け切ったとき
老倉先輩は思ったでしょうね
When the body had decomposed to a point that rendered it unidentifiable as such,
お母さんがどこかにいった と
Oikura thought her mother had left.
水が蒸発するようなものですよ
It's like the boiling water.
自分の力で沸騰したと思っている水が嫌い でしたっけ?
She said she hates water that thinks it boils without assistance, right?
ええ だけどお母様は 言うなら
自力で沸騰したわけですね
Well, her mother boiled without assistance.
水
Water.
She boiled and evaporated.
つまり老倉先輩のお母様もまた
蒸発したということ
She hasn't left the room.
お母様は 部屋から出ていないんですよ
煙のように消えたのではなく
She didn't disappear like smoke would.
水のように消えたのです
She disappeared like water.
だけど人間はすべてが水分じゃないだろ
Well, human beings aren't composed of only water.
残りはどうなるんだ?
What about the rest?
そりゃあ ゴミ屋敷が処分されるときに
ゴミと一緒に処分されたんじゃないですかね?
I assume they threw it out with the rest of the junk when the house was cleaned out.
つまり... なんだ
So this is...
餓死による自殺... ってことになるのか?
Suicide by starvation?
さてどうでしょう
I don't really think so.
生きる気力をなくしていたとはいえ
自殺とは違うと私は思いますがね
She surely lost the will to live on, but I don't think that's the same thing as suicide.
生きる気力を失うのと 死にたくなるのは
人心としてはまた違うものですし
Losing the will to live and wanting to die are two different things.
羽川先輩はどう思います?
What do you think, Hanekawa?
私はただ 老倉さんがこのことを知らずに
これからもずっと知らずに 生きていけたらいいと思うだけだよ
I just think it would be best if Oikura was never told of this.
ただまあ 本人も薄々
おかしいとは思っているんでしょう
Perhaps, but I'm sure Oikura knows something is wrong.
何かがおかしい
That something doesn't fit.
自分は何かを誤魔化している気がする
That she is hiding something.
何かに気付いていない振りをしている気がする
That she is pretending to not understand something.
I'm sure she's felt that way these past three years.
そんな思いがあったのでしょう この三年
And she will feel that for the rest of her life.
そしてこれから一生
No, I will end it today.
いや 今日までだ
僕が話す
I'll talk to her.
僕から話す
She will hear it from me.
今から老倉の部屋に戻って
全部 話してくる
I'll go back to her and tell her everything.
そろそろ役場の人も帰った頃だろ
The people from town hall have surely left by now.
僕一人で行くよ
I'll go alone.
二人はここで待っててくれたらいい
Please wait for me here.
あ 阿良々木くん... 本気?
Are you sure, Araragi?
本気だよ
Yeah.
さっきも言っただろ?
I told you earlier.
僕はずっと 老倉のことを見て見ぬ振りをしてきた
I've pretended not to see her for a long time now.
六年以上もだ
For more than six years.
あいつが母親の死を直視できなかったように
Just like she was oblivious to her mother's death,
僕はあいつを直視できなかった
I was oblivious to her.
だからこそ 僕はもう老倉を
これ以上は見過ごせない
I can't leave her alone now.
どんなことになるかわかりませんよ 阿良々木先輩
There's no telling what will happen, Araragi.
今以上に嫌われることになるかも
She might start to hate you even more.
今以上に嫌われることはないから大丈夫だ
She can't possibly hate me any more.
あったとしても 僕が嫌われることで
その分あいつが自分を好きになれるなら まあ そっちのほうがいいな
Even if she could, I'm fine with that if it lets her love herself.
ほんの少しだけ先んじた その道の先輩として
I'll teach her how to be happy,
あいつに幸せになる方法を教えてやろう
though my experience is little more than hers.
But my student is the outstanding Oikura.
まあとはいえ 生徒はなにせあの優秀極まる老倉だ
幸せについても ちょっとコツさえつかんでしまえば
Once she gets the hang of it,
I'm sure she'll surpass me in no time.
すぐに追い抜かされることになるのだろうけれど
幸せというのは 競争じゃあないしな
But happiness isn't a competition.
追い越されたなら
今度は僕があいつから教えてもらえばいいだけの話だ
When she surpasses me, I can then learn from her.
Together we will study, learn, and become better people.
そうしてお互い 学び合い 教え合い 高め合えばいい
勉強会を開こう
Let us have a study session.
底抜けに愚かな僕達だけれど
We two are limitless fools,
一緒に 賢くなろう
but let us become wise together.
ちゃんと 幸せになろう
Let us be happy.
阿良々木先輩
Araragi.
Will you repay your debt with further injury?
あなたは恩を仇(あだ)で返すのですか?
たとえ仇でも 老倉に返せるものがあって
本当によかった
I'm glad I have something to repay her with, even if it will hurt her.
Sodachi Lost
Now for the epilogue—Or rather, the outcome.
後日談というか 今回のオチ
翌日 二人の妹 火憐と月火に起こされて
僕は学校に向かう
The next day I was woken up by my little sisters,
Karen and Tsukihi, and went on my way to school.
その際 僕は二人の妹に 小学生の頃
一時的にこの家に保護されていた子供のことを覚えているかどうかを 訊いてみた
I asked my little sisters whether they remembered
a girl staying at our place for a while in grade school.
二人とも覚えていないとのことだった
Both said they didn't.
結局 老倉は学校に来ない
Oikura wouldn't come to school.
今日学校に行っても 僕が老倉に会うことはない
Even if I went today, she isn't there.
交わした約束は反故(ほご)にされた形だが
しかしそれはやむを得ないことでもあった
Our deal had to be scrapped,
but there was nothing we could do.
今 役場の人に言われちゃった
補助の額が今の半分くらいになるから
The people from the town hall told me that my welfare would be cut in half.
もうここには住み続けられないんだってさ
They said I can't stay here either.
って言っても大丈夫
But I'll be fine.
もう少し小さな公営マンションが見つかったって話だし
They found me a smaller apartment.
だから私 引っ越すことになる
I have to move.
直江津高校から転校することになる
I'll transfer away from Naoetsu High School.
このときの彼女は驚くほど穏やかだった
She was incredibly calm as she said that.
たぶん 二人で会えば 二人で話せば
老倉はこんな感じなのだ
This is what she's like when I'm the only one around,
中学一年生のときの夏休みのように
just like in middle school during summer break.
僕が話した 彼女の母についての推測も
老倉は拍子抜けするほどあっさり受け入れた
When I told her of our conjecture regarding her mother,
her immediate acceptance was anticlimactic.
I see.
そう
やっぱり そうだよね
I had a hunch, I guess.
もうすぐこの町を離れなきゃいけないことはわかってたんだけど
I knew I'd have to leave this town soon,
ほら そのタイミングで鉄条が休むってわかったから
私 学校に行ったのよ
but when Tetsujou went on leave, I went back to school.
何かがあるかもしれない
何かが変わるかもしれないと思って
I thought something might happen, something might change.
そうしたら...
And then—
それから僕は老倉と少し話して
それから家に帰った
I talked to her some more and went home.
どこにも寄らなかった
No detours.
そんなわけで 今日の僕は 教室で老倉と会う心配をすることなく
学校に向かうのだが
And so today I am unafraid of seeing her in class as I go to school.
はーい 阿良々木先輩
'Sup, Araragi.
That's no way to talk to your senior.
はーいじゃねえよ
ねえ扇ちゃん
Hey, Ougi.
昨日 なんで先に帰っちゃったの?
Why did you go home without me yesterday?
待っててって言ったじゃん
I told you to wait for me.
羽川先輩に帰ろうと言われまして
Hanekawa suggested we go home.
なんで羽川 そんなこと言ってんだ
Why did she say that?
いい感じに言ってましたよ
She meant well.
二人きりにしてあげよう みたいな感じで
She wanted to give you some privacy with her.
いや いい感じに言ってんじゃねえよ
Don't put it like that.
きみ達が広場からいなくなってて
どれくらいびっくりしたと思ってるんだ
I was really startled when I didn't find you two in the square.
昨日の件は 私の負けです
I lost yesterday.
申し訳ありません
I'm very sorry.
正直見くびっていました
Frankly, I underestimated you.
てっきり阿良々木先輩は
しっぽを巻くと思っていましたからね
I thought you'd turn tail and run.
最後に思わぬ根性を見せつけられてしまいました
You showed unexpected courage at the end.
Private High School
なんだか 不思議でもあるんだけどな
You know, it's pretty weird.
The day you transferred here,
Tetsujou went on maternity leave,
Naoetsu Private High School
きみが転校してきた途端 鉄条が産休を取ったり
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
Oikura came back to school,
Naoetsu Private High School
老倉が学校に来たり
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
and now she's transferred out again.
Naoetsu Private High School
そうかと思えば転校して行ったり
停まっていたものが なあなあで誤魔化していたものが
さながら思い出したかのように 急激に動き出す感じ
The things I brushed under the carpet or left alone jolt into action like memories risen from the deep.
へえ 老倉先輩 転校なさるんですか
Oh, is Oikura transferring schools?
知りませんでしたあ
I didn't know.
いいキャスティングだったんですけれどねえ
She was cast so well, too.
でも本当
転校先ではうまくやれるといいですね
I do hope she'll be happy wherever she goes now.
誰も彼女を知らない新天地でなら
きっと成功なさるでしょう
I'm sure she'll be successful on greener pastures where no one knows her.
阿良々木先輩のおかげで
Because of you.
おかげさまで
Thanks to you.
扇ちゃんは こんなところで何をしているの?
What are you doing here, Ougi?
Do you live here?
家 この辺なの?
ちょっと迷子を探してましてね
I'm looking for a girl who's lost.
元々はそこがスタートだったんですから
That is, in the end, how it all begins.
I lost this round.
今回は私の負けです
でも せめてもの負け惜しみを言わせてもらうなら
Permit me to be a sore loser,
あくまでも初手(しょて)は様子見でしたからね
but the first round is a training session anyway.
あなたが幼なじみ相手にどんな風に振る舞うのか
How were you going to treat your childhood friend?
見たかったという目的は果たせたのですから
I accomplished my goal of finding that out.
バランス的には負けるくらいでちょうどよかったとも言えます
Losing is perfect as far as balance is concerned.
気をつけてくださいね 阿良々木先輩
Be careful, Araragi.
次はこんなにうまく行くとは限りませんよ
There's no guarantee it'll go so well next time.
一寸先が闇なのは
The future is shrouded in darkness
even when the sun is up.
夜道だけではありませんから
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part Three
Black
そっか... 残念
I see. Too bad.
老倉さんとは 仲良くなれると思ったのに
I thought I'd really hit it off with her.
まあ 老倉さんの新しい門出を祝おうか 今は
Let us pray she finds happiness in her new life.
そうだな
Yeah.
扇ちゃんもそんなことを言ってたよ
Ougi said that too.
阿良々木くん 私
休学届を出さなきゃいけないから、
Araragi, I have to hand in a form of temporary absence.
先に教室に行っといてくれる?
Can you go ahead to the classroom?
おう わかった
Sure.
って休学届...?
Uh, temporary absence?
え? なに お前も直江津高校をやめるの?
Are you leaving Naoetsu High School too?
違うって 休学休学
No, temporary. Temporary!
ほら 卒業したら私が行く予定の放浪旅行 あるじゃない
When I graduate I want to drift around the world for a while,
そのロケハンに行ってこようかなって思って
so I thought I'd look at a couple of locations.
軽く世界一周してくる
I'll make a couple of stops around the world.
一ヵ月ほど留守にするけど よろしくね
I'll be back in a month. Take care of things here, please.
旅の途中で忍野さんをお見かけしたら
声をかけとくから
If I run into Oshino somewhere, I'll talk to him.
んじゃ もしもどこかで忍野に会ったら
姪っ子に会ったって言ってやれよ
Tell him we met his niece if you see him.
うん まあそう言いにいくようなものだよ
Yes. That's one of my main goals.
No subject
Mark as unread
To Koyokoyo,
Totally broke finger
Going to hospital before school today
To Koyokoyo,
Totally broke finger
Going to hospital before school today
Don't write like a telegram.
なんで電報風なんだよ
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
Yokoyoko?
横横?
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
To Yokoyoko
Oikura came to apologize this morning.
Forgave her.
I'm fine
(but I have a broken finger)
戦場ヶ原と仲直りするというほうの約束は
どうやら老倉は守ってくれたらしい
It looks like Oikura kept the part of the promise that meant making up with Senjougahara.
よかった
That's good.
旅に出る前に 羽川にもこのメールを見せてやらねば
I need to show this message to Hanekawa before she leaves.
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
Koyokoyo, I'm sorry you're worried.
I'll give you lots of deep kisses on our next date, okay?
Deeply addicted to your kiss
I can't show her this message.
見せられねえメールになってんじゃねえか!
Message from Oikura.
Says "under the desk"
Yours, better half
Message from Oikura.
Says "under the desk"
Yours, better half
"Yours, better half"?
あなたの左より?
何の挨拶だ
What kind of salutation is that?
かつて 五年前の夏休み
僕は廃屋の卓袱台の裏に
Did I not find the same envelope five years ago, during summer vacation, taped to the underside of a coffee table?
同じような封筒を見つけたのではなかったか
ただ あのときの封筒は空っぽだった
The envelope back then was empty.
I could feel the paper inside this time.
今回は便箋が入っていることが
手触りでわかった
There was no sender or receiver on it,
宛名も差出人も
表にも裏にも書いていない封筒だったが
but I knew full well who taped this to my desk.
しかし 誰がこれを
僕の机に張り付けたのかは明白だった
老倉育
Oikura Sodachi.
あいつはすべての約束を守ったのだ
She kept all her promises.
前触れもなくいきなりいなくなる
Vanishing unheralded
seems to be no longer part of her repertoire.
老倉は そんな彼女では
とりあえずなくなったようである
Not much had changed, but at least something had.
小さな変化だが 彼女の変化だった
その事実は嬉しくもあり 先を行かれたようで
ちょっと寂しくもあった
That made me glad, but seeing her walk ahead also saddened me.
ここは僕も成長したところを見せなければと
To show her that I, too, had matured,
五年前のようにびりびりに破いたりせず
I opened the letter carefully
できるだけ丁寧に封筒を開けて
without ripping it open like I did five years earlier.
Within I found countless sheets of paper.
中から複数枚の便箋を取り出す
さて 手紙の内容は数学のクイズだろうか
What were the contents of this letter? Math questions?
それともらしくもないお礼状だろうか
Unbefitting words of gratitude?
あるいは罵倒のメッセージだろうか
Strings of abuse?
そのすべてということもあり得るけれど
All of it was possible.
Let's see.
僕は思わず綻(ほころ)んでしまった
I broke into a broad smile.
なあ
Hey.
なんて書いてあったと思う?
What do you think was written there?
I hear your laughter near me
You were supposed to be there forever
I breathed onto the classroom window and wrote your name
only to panic and wipe it with my sleeve
I heard your voice from the hallway
and went home in hurry to hide my feelings
At some point I became unable
to talk to you normally
I can hear your laughter a ways away
You were supposed to be next to me forever
You knew how I felt
even when I said nothing
Now I know how important you were to me,
but we will never see each other again